today we enter into our last week of מסכת עירובין Masechet Eruvin
and well I would say you know this last פרק perek is
obviously a very significant change it's much less about עירובין Eruvin and
much more about carrying in רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid and so on
and also special exceptions for כתבי קודש Kitvei Kodesh it is interesting
how it does parallel towards the end of שבת Shabbat where we
had special exceptions of being caught outside of the תחום techum with
a לולב lulav on.
Anyway so we continue now in the גמרא Gemara today's דף daf
is צדי חת Tzadi Chet 98 and we continue in the גמרא
Gemara two lines from the bottom of צדי זין עמוד בית Tzadi
Zayin Amud Bet after it picks up from the משנה. Mishnah. The
משנה Mishnah said that if somebody is reading on a porch and
the
and a ספר sefer that they are reading whether a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah some some book of כתבי קודש Kitvei Kodesh rolls from
their hand then they can roll it back. Now the principle here
is called אוגדו בידו Ogdo BeYado the the
the knot is in your hand which means that if you have
a long if you have something like a long stick and part
of it is in רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid and you're in רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim and you're holding on or the vice versa and
you're holding on to one end and you pull the other end
towards you you did not do a full act of הוצאה Hotza'ah
because the whole object did not fully begin in one domain and
move to the other. So here too if you're reading the book
and it rolls off of your porch into a רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabbiim and you roll it back to you that would only be
rabbinic anyway even if it's from רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim to רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid because it is not fully in רשות הרבים. Reshut
HaRabbiim. The whole thing is one unit you don't divide the papers
they're all physically connected and therefore it would only be rabbinic. So
the question is going to be are we going to allow rabbinic
violation for the sake of כתבי קודש Kitvei Kodesh or not?
So the משנה Mishnah says by if you're on the porch you
can roll it up towards you without any qualification. Then it says
if you have the similar scenario and you're on a rooftop and
it rolls down then it starts making distinctions where the first opinion
is
once it's within the ten טפחים tefachim of the רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabbiim here I'll draw it for you to start here you are
because I just need to use my artistic skills one last time
okay before we end this פרק. perek. Here we are and here's
you with your ספר sefer okay
and here the ספר sefer has started has fallen down and here's
the other end but you're holding on to one part of the
scroll and over here is the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim okay.
So it says that if the bottom of it is within higher
than ten טפחים tefachim from the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim it's not
in the air space of the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim then you
can roll it up. Once it enters the air space of רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim you cannot roll it up. That seems to say
we're not going to give you any allowance as soon as it
becomes even a rabbinic problem you know cause this would only be
a rabbinic problem cause you're holding on to one end as soon
as it becomes even a rabbinic problem you do not you are
not able to roll it up. That's the first opinion. Then it
said one minute then it says so what do you do so
you reverse it so that the script is against the wall and
it's protected from the elements. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is more lenient
he says as long as it's even if it's a our version
is מחט makhat a needle's breath the גמרא's Gemara version seemed to
be
not מחט makhat but we'll see what the גמרא Gemara has another
word for I'm trying to remember
anyway the גמרא's Gemara version was חוט khut even a string's breath
even if it was a millimeter off the ground as long as
it hasn't hit the ground you can roll it up. And then
we have the final position רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says even if
it's hit the ground this whole thing is rabbinic so you're allowed
to violate rabbinic okay but the first positions were more limited. So
the first question the גמרא's Gemara going to have is why do
we have all of these distinctions and or about how close is
it to the ground by the roof and that wasn't discussed by
the case of the porch. So let's take a look now at
the גמרא Gemara two lines
from the bottom הי
עקירה והי הנחה hi akirah ve hi anacha well is he really
doing a עקירה akirah is a question also because it's suspended in
air right okay but even if he's doing a עקירה akirah if
it's hit the ground it's still only rabbinic because it's not fully
in one domain. Okay but the other positions don't don't like when
it's hit the ground don't want don't allow it when it's hit
the ground but the question is what why are there no debates
why by the case of the porch so let's take a look
from the גמרא Gemara two lines from the bottom. So the גמרא
Gemara says I'll get back to you one second האי אסקופה היכי
דמי hai iskopa heichi dami what's the case of the porch אילימא
אסקופה רשות היחיד ileima iskopa reshut hayachid let's say it's a porch
you know that's ten טפחים tefachim high and four טפחים tefachim wide
so the porch is in front of your house and it's רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid and קמה kamma and in front of it is
רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim is a public domain okay. So our question
is immediately why is that different than the rooftop but let's just
see how the גמרא Gemara analyzes this on its own terms. ולא
גזרינן דילמא נפל ואתי לאתויי Velo gazrinan dimalma nafal ve'ati le'atuyei we're
not afraid that if we let him roll it up he's going
to come and you know maybe it'll fall and then he'll come
why if we let him roll it up then even if it
totally falls out of his hand and it falls into the domain
maybe he'll come and take it back home. So you're telling me
no we're not concerned about that since he's holding on to it
not a problem
okay. So if that's true which position if that's true if it
came from the porch and it's rolled into the רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabbiim and touching the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbiim and it's not a
problem which position does that correspond to by the debate about the
roof. roof. Or we had three opinions by the roof: it has
to be higher than ten טפחים, Tefachim, it has to be even
a millimeter off the ground, or even if it hits the ground.
So it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the one that says even if
it hits the ground. Okay, so so then this position about the
porch would be the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon position of the roof.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says, top of צדיק ח' עמוד
א', Tzadik Cheit Amud Aleph, מאני? Mani? Who is this? רבי שמעון
היא, Rabbi Shimon hee, it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר כל דבר
שהוא משום שבות, d'amar kol davar shehu mishum shvus, anything that is
rabbinic, okay, שבות shvus is a word for rabbinic prohibitions of שבת,
Shabbos, אין עומד בפני כתבי הקדש ein omeid bifnei kisvei hakodesh will
not get in the way of protecting holy scriptures. So he's doing
up about the theme of תפילין, Tefillin, but by תפילין Tefillin as
well remember we didn't actually violate, we did ways of doing it
without violating. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is taking it one step
further and says even if it is a rabbinic problem, I don't
care if it's to protect כתבי הקדש. Kisvei Hakodesh. Okay, so אימא
סיפא, eima seifa, so now let's look at the case of the
roof. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אפילו אינו סילוק מן
הארץ אלא מלא החוט, afilu eino siluk min ha'aretz ela mlo hachut,
here there's מלא החוט, mlo hachut, even if it's only a string's
breadth, a hair's breadth off of the ground, גוללו אצלו. golelo etzlo.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, אפילו בארץ עצמה גוללו אצלו, afilu
ba'aretz atzma golelo etzlo,
even if it's on the ground you can do it. So by
the roof we have the debate and רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's opinion
is last. By the porch we only have one opinion that says
no problem. So how is this? רישא וסיפא רבי שמעון, reisha v'seifa
Rabbi Shimon, the beginning by the porch is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
the last opinion by the roof is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, מציעתא
רבי יהודה, metziata Rabbi Yehuda,
and then in the middle we have all these other opinions? Like
how is it that the porch case was not debated and it
was סתם stam was רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and then you had
this roof case which was a three-way debate? And the גמרא Gemara
only focus on two ways, but it was a three-way debate anyway.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, אין,
in, yeah, רישא וסיפא רבי שמעון מציעתא רבי יהודה, reisha v'seifa Rabbi
Shimon metziata Rabbi Yehuda, big deal. Okay, right, which is, yeah, the
case by the porch was a סתם stam position but it was
following רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position, and then in the case of
the roof we mention debates, but really those debates would be true
about the porch as well, it's not a difference between the porch
and the roof, and the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon mentioned at the
end of the issue about the roof was the opinion by the
case of the porch. Okay, so fine, that's saying in terms of
the question why is the porch different than the roof? The answer
is it isn't, the case of the porch is going according to
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, now רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, I'm sorry,
רבה אמר, Rabba amar, now רבה Rabba doesn't like that, he'd rather
that the case of the porch be something substantively different. So he
says, הכא באסקופה הנדרסת
עסקינן. hacha beskufa hanidreses askinan. We're talking about a porch that has
a lot of traffic. It's true רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
and in that way it's not different, but it has a lot
of traffic. ומשום בזיון כתבי הקדש שרו רבנן, umishum bizayon kisvei hakodesh
sharu rabbanan,
and this would be a case that everybody would agree we would
allow a rabbinic issue to protect כתבי הקדש kisvei hakodesh when it's
really going to be like a בזיון bizayon denigrated. So people are,
yeah, what? You're going into רשות הרבים reshus harabim isn't enough?
Is this the case where it's running into רשות הרבים? reshus harabim?
Oh, that's true, I suppose you're right, you could say that a
little bit that the scroll has gone so much into the רשות
הרבים reshus harabim that they're going to that they're going to walk
over it, I suppose that could have been a scenario as well,
but it's assuming even if a little bit went into the רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. So here you are, you're on your porch in
front of your house, right, here's your house or whatever, this is
your house back here, you're on your porch and here's the רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, okay, but for whatever reason, okay maybe this isn't
a porch, maybe it's a portico or something like that, and whatever
reason people regularly walk through, okay, and therefore you're here, right,
and your scroll's rolled off and you know maybe it's only a
little bit in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, if you turn it over
and go home and leave it, people are going to trample on
it, and therefore that's a case where everybody agrees we allow rabbinic
issues to be overwritten in order to preserve כתבי הקדש. kisvei hakodesh.
Unless it's being trampled on?
What? Oh that's true. That's what רבה Rabba says. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, so the
גמרא Gemara says, איתיביה, eisivei, I'll ask you on that, אביי Abaye
challenge, איתיביה אביי, eisivei Abaye, אביי Abaye challenged. Now this is a
challenge on רבה Rabba who was the last opinion, but it could
equally have been raised on the previous opinion. But anyway, now we're
dealing with רבה's Rabba's opinion. So אביי Abaye asked, תוך ארבע אמות,
toch arba amos, we have a ברייתא braisa and the ברייתא braisa
says, if it's rolled away from you, within ארבע אמות, arba amos,
גוללו אצלו, golelo etzlo, you can roll it up to you. חוץ
לארבע אמות, chutz l'arba amos, more than ארבע אמות arba amos away
from you, like you know into the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, הופכו
על הכתב, hofcho al haksav, you turn it upside down. Now by
the way it hadn't occurred to me but what Michael was saying
is a reasonable explanation about that, that if it's more than ארבע
אמות arba amos then it's in the middle of רשות הרבים reshus
harabim more and maybe people will walk on it, maybe that's the
explanation. But ארבע אמות arba amos is a classic halachic issue about
carrying in רשות הרבים reshus harabim or whatever, let's take a look
at what אביי Abaye says.
So אביי Abaye understands that this is a ברייתא braisa that is
clarifying the case of the porch on the משנה mishna that even
when we allow the porch we only allow it within ארבע אמות.
arba amos. So he says like this, ואי אמרת באסקופה הנדרסת עסקינן,
v'ee amarta beskufa hanidreses askinan, if it's a porch that's trampled on,
מה לי תוך ארבע אמות מה לי חוץ לארבע אמות, ma lee
toch arba amos ma lee chutz l'arba amos, what difference does it
make if it's within or outside of ארבע אמות? arba amos? If
basically meaning if you're saying you're doing it in a way that
doesn't violate, then you could say somehow once it's ארבע אמות arba
amos that's another violation. But if you're telling me it does violate
but it's overridden because of concerns of protecting כתבי הקדש, kisvei hakodesh,
then what
At the end of the day, it's rabbinic issues that should be
overridden to preserve כתבי קודש kisvei kodesh cause people are trampling on
the porch. So אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye
says here's somehow I'm going to explain the case of the porch
and that the four amos makes a difference. הכא באיסקופא כרמלית עסקינן
hacha b'iskopa karmelis askinan ורשות הרבים עוברת לפניה. v'reshus harabim overes l'faneha.
Okay, so we're not talking the rooftop, why is there a debate
by the rooftop? Because the rooftop's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. This
porch is less than עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high.
Okay, so this porch is, here's your
porch, okay, and it's only, I don't know, nine טפחים tefachim high,
okay? And it's got a רשות הרבים reshus harabim there, so the
porch is a כרמלית, karmelis, okay? And if the porch is a
כרמלית, karmelis, so now even when something rolls off of the porch
into the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, in a way it's a double
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. It's number one only a דרבנן d'rabbanan because it's not
fully in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and number two it's only
a דרבנן d'rabbanan because you're only going from רשות הרבים reshus harabim
to כרמלית. karmelis. So it's, you know, more of an attenuated איסור,
issur, and that's what makes the case of the porch different. Now
how is the four amos going to be different? No, because we
don't סתם stam allow double דרבננים. d'rabbanans. Now why is the four
amos going to make a difference? We don't. Because it's still אסור.
assur. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: הכא באיסקופא כרמלית עסקינן
hacha b'iskopa karmelis askinan ורשות הרבים עוברת לפניה v'reshus harabim overes l'faneha
and you have a רשות הרבים reshus harabim passing by it. תוך
ארבע אמות, toch arba amos, if it falls within four amos, דאי
נפלו ומייתי לה, d'ee naflu u'maisi lah, לא אתי לידי חיוב חטאת,
lo asi lidei chiyuv chatas, it is impossible in that scenario for
there to be even, not only are you not violating a דרבנן,
d'rabbanan, there's not even a concern you might come to violate a
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Because look at what you do. It falls within four
amos, right? If this is only three amos and you're going to
carry it, so A, you're not carrying it, I mean you're not
carrying it, you're going to roll it up, right? So even were
you to go down and pick it up and carry it, you
wouldn't go
four amos in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and you're going from רשות
הרבים reshus harabim to כרמלית. karmelis. So if it's within three amos,
there's no scenario you could, not only is it a double דרבנן,
d'rabbanan, there's no scenario you could transgress a דאורייתא, d'oraisa, even if
you were to say, oh, if they let me roll it up,
I might as well go pick it up. But once this is
four amos, if we let you roll it up, then you might
come to pick it up and carry it, and then we're going
to have to prohibit it.
That's why I'm not saying, let's say I'm just reading my letter,
yeah, and it rolled in within three amos in the כרמלית, karmelis,
am I allowed to pick it up? We're not allowed to roll
it back?
No, you cannot carry from a רשות הרבים reshus harabim to a
כרמלית, karmelis, of course not. Even by אגדו בידו, egdo b'yado, that's
still a rabbinic prohibition. So
even, yes, we have rabbinic prohibition of רשות הרבים reshus harabim to
כרמלית, karmelis, we have a rabbinic prohibition of אגדו בידו, egdo b'yado,
and even when they come together it's still rabbinically prohibited. Okay, but
it's just more somewhat attenuated. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
so
תוך
ארבע אמות דאי נפלו ומייתי לה, toch arba amos d'ee naflu u'maisi
lah, if it falls down completely and you go and pick it
up לא אתי לידי חיוב חטאת, lo asi lidei chiyuv chatas, you
won't get to a biblical transgression, literally it says you won't have
to ever bring a חטאת chatas because it's inadvertent here, it's not
willful. שרו ליה רבנן, sharu lei rabbanan, the רבנן rabbanan will allow
you. חוץ לארבע אמות, chutz l'arba amos, once it's outside of four
amos, דאי מייתי לה, d'ee maisi lah, that if in a case
where it actually you went to pick it up, it actually fully
fell out of your hands, right, it wouldn't matter if you went
and picked it up if half of it is in the other
domain, but if it fully fell out of your hands and you
went and carried it, דאי מייתי אתי לידי חיוב חטאת, d'ee maisi
asi lidei chiyuv chatas, that then you would come to transgress a
דאורייתא, d'oraisa, לא שרו ליה רבנן, lo sharu lei rabbanan, the רבנן
rabbanan won't allow it. Thank you. So according to אביי, Abaye, one
answer was that when there's a high danger to the כתבי קודש,
kisvei kodesh, we override דרבננים, d'rabbanans, כרמלית karmelis and the rest. This
answer is saying no, even it's just a normal concern of exposure
and where the end of the משנה mishna made it clear that
generally we don't allow דרבננים, d'rabbanans, it has to be higher than
עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim or whatever it is, we don't allow override.
But here there will be cases where we will allow override when
the איסור issur is much less. What is the איסור issur much
less? It's number one, it's a דרבנן d'rabbanan of a דרבנן, d'rabbanan,
so it's already attenuated, and number two there's no concern of transgressing
a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So in that scenario, everybody, even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who argues on רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, would admit that we
would allow you to do it to protect כתבי קודש. kisvei kodesh.
And let's say it's like money over there, so you turned it
over?
All right, so then that might, so then maybe that would be
different. It's not clear exactly all the parameters.
מיהו חוץ ותוך ארבע אמות מאי אמרת? mihu chutz v'toch arba amos
mai amart?
Who knows? Who knows, right? We don't know, we don't know what
אביי Abaye would say in a case
about מותר בבזיון. mutar b'bizayon. Would they have would he also agree
that even the more strict opinions would say that there's a certain
threshold that yes, you could even violate a straight דרבנן? d'rabbanan? That
we don't know. Okay, but that's what given explanations that are being
put out there. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אי הכי,
ee hachi, if that's true, תוך ארבע אמות נמי נגזר דילמא מייתי
מרשות הרבים לרשות היחיד. toch arba amos nami nigzar dilma maisi me'reshus
harabim l'reshus hayachid. So okay, but even if it's three amos, you're
going to if we're concerned about is it possible to transgress a
דאורייתא, d'oraisa, yes, because you'll pick it up from the רשות הרבים
reshus harabim and you'll bring it to רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Now
what רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? You're bringing it to your porch, but
what's the porch in front of?
Presumably where are most porches in front of? House. Your house. So
and presumably you're not going to. leave your books outside on the
porch. It's a nice beautiful day. You go out to the porch
to read a book, but then you bring it back in, right?
So of course if that were really true, even if it weren't,
didn't roll, why, you know, we should be concerned you'll take it
from the porch into the house. But okay, so maybe normally, if
nothing had happened, it would have started on the porch and stayed
on the porch. But now let's be concerned that you might go
pick it up and then just bring it inside. So therefore, what
do you mean there's no concern about a דאורייתא? d'oraisa? If that's
the issue, there is a concern about a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Now as
I said, it's easy to distinguish, you know, anyway you know not
to go from the כרמלית carmelis to the house, but anyway let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. וכי תימא v'chi teima and
if you say כיון דמפסקא—מפסקתא—מפסקתא—מפסקא, thank you, I don't know what's wrong
with me today. כיון דמפסקא כרמלית לית לן בה, keivan d'mafseka carmelis
leis lan bah, since the
כרמלית carmelis
is—is divided, you know, separates your house and the רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, we're not concerned because you would have to do two things.
If it rolled away within four
אמות—if amot it rolled away within four אמות amot for you and
back—and the whole thing fell out of your hand, right? So for
you to transgress, you'd have to pick it up, go
into the כרמלית, carmelis, and from the כרמלית carmelis into the house.
Okay, so maybe that much, meaning if to say you'd have to
pick it up and walk, you might walk four אמות, amot, that's
one act. But here you'd actually have to go over and through
a כרמלית, carmelis, so maybe that degree of concern, you know, that's
already something not to be concerned about. You know, you'll remember, you're
going on your porch, you don't go from your porch then to
your house. So if you say that, then that's why we're not
concerned. ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, but doesn't רבא Rava say המעביר חפץ
מתחלת ארבע
לסוף ארבע—והעבירו דרך עליו חייב—that chayav. if you take an object and
you bring it from the beginning of four אמות amot to the
end of four אמות, amot, you're חייב. chayav. Now what does that
mean? Okay, what is רבא Rava saying and how is it relevant
to the discussion? So there's a debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says what it means is, let's say I pick
up an object in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, carry it higher than
ten אמות—ten amot טפחים—and tefachim I walk my four אמות amot and
then I put it down. So the space it went when it
went the four אמות amot was not רשות הרבים reshus harabbim space,
and רבא Rava says even so you're חייב. chayav Okay, fine. How
is that relevant to our discussion? It's relevant to our discussion because
the גמרא Gemara says maybe this is why the גמרא Gemara was
saying I shouldn't have to worry about the porch. Not that you'll
remember when you hit the porch and you won't take it in.
That's the גמרא's Gemara going to say in a minute. But maybe
it's saying like this: maybe you're not חייב chayav. if you go
from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim to רשות היחיד reshus hayachid but you
go through neutral zone, you know, safe zone, כרמלית carmelis is neutral
as it were, maybe you don't transgress. Maybe you only transgress when
you stay in danger zones, not when you pass through a neutral
zone. So it says no, you see it's not true, because רבא
Rava says I pick it up from רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, I
carry it over my head, and I put it down, I went
through this neutral zone, it doesn't matter. So going through a כרמלית,
carmelis, who cares if it's a neutral zone? If you wound up
picking it up from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and putting it down
in your house, you're going to be
חייב. chayav. Okay, that's how רש״י Rashi explains it. תוספות Tosafot explains
that רבא—that Rava that's obvious, the גמרא Gemara never had a question
about that. He says what רבא Rava is saying is differently. Not
I carried it over my head. רבא Rava is saying let's say
I pick up an object here and this is in, you know,
in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and I transfer it here and I
go like this and I put it down. Now, okay, outside. So
what's the question? Of course you're חייב. No, maybe the fact that
it stopped here when it hit me and hit dead center, and
we were centered, and it actually stopped for a moment as I
transferred hands, maybe that's like a הנחה. hanachah. Okay, so that's רבא's
Rava position. רבא Rava said, I'm sorry, it's not, it's a constant
movement and so on. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, you know,
maybe I would have said the same thing. If you go ahead
and you pick it up, and let's say what you actually do
when you pick it up is you reach over into the רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, right, and you pick it up, and say for—and
maybe you deposit it into your house, or some scenario like that,
maybe that should exempt you? No, I'm sorry, that is not considered
a הנחה. hanachah. So either way the גמרא Gemara says just by
going through the כרמלית, carmelis, if you wound up going into the
house, you will have performed
a הנחה—I hanachah mean you will have performed a הוצאה hotza'ah and
it's a problem. So why would we
allow—why is the case of the porch—why is there a substantive difference
between inside four אמות amot and outside four אמות? amot? If the
four אמות amot is a problem that you might come to do
a carrying, then even three אמות amot should be a problem you
might come to do a carrying and bring it into your house.
Let's just see the גמרא's Gemara answer. So it
says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, very interesting answer, באסקופא
ארוכה, b'askupa arucha, that you've got a very long porch. Now very
long doesn't mean long side the way of רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
it's more like it's like, you know, sort of like a pier,
okay? It's very long, so if you were to pick it up
and you're at the edge of your porch and before—by the time
it would take you to walk it into your house,
אדהכי והכי, adeihachi v'hachi, מדכר, midkar, by the time you got back
to the house you'd remember. Okay, so basically saying the presence of
the porch—I mean if you want to just say it roughly, it's
saying no. is not as much of a concern, there's a much
more reasonable concern you'll pick it up and walk four אמות amot
in רשות הרבים reshut harabim than you'll pick it up from רשות
הרבים reshut harabim and take it all the way into your house.
But it says that for that gives the scenario that the porch
is very long, so there's time to remember and therefore it's not
a concern.
There's more than four אמות amot and we're worried you're going to
be אי בעית אימא,
Ee ba'it eima, and if you want I could say, yes, דאולם
בשיפופא שאינה ארוכה, de-ulam be-shipufa she-eina arucha, it's not such a long
or wide porch, וסתם כתבי קודש עיוני מעייני בהו ומנח להו. ve-stam
kitvei kodesh iyunei me'aynei behu u-manach lehu. What have you been doing
on the porch? You've been
reading your ספר. sefer. So if you go ahead and get it
from the רשות הרבים reshut harabim and return it to the porch,
what's the most likely thing for you to do now? Go back
to reading your ספר. sefer. So therefore, once you get it on
your porch, you're going to stop. If you know if it fell
four אמות amot into רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you're going to carry
it the whole four אמות amot if you forget. But if it
fell within four אמות amot and you carried it from the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim to your porch, you're going to stop on your
porch and get back to reading. So basically, according to this, the
idea of the reason the porch is different is that it's a
כרמלית, karmelit, so we're only dealing with a rabbinic issue, and it's
a דאורייתא, de-oraita, a double דרבנן, derabanan, a rabbinic with the rolling
up with the אוגדו בידו, ogdo beyado, and it's a double דרבנן,
derabanan, and even and therefore everybody would agree that's okay in order
to protect כתבי קודש kitvei kodesh if it's only a double דרבנן.
derabanan. But but even there, outside of four אמות amot is going
to be אסור, asur, because that then risks possibly transgressing a דאורייתא.
de-oraita. Okay, you had a question, Paula.
Well, you were talking about handing it and then handing it. What
if you took it, put it down, and then picked it up?
No, then of course you're פטור, patur, that's exactly what a הנחה
hanacha is. It's placing it down.
Yeah, if you did put it down.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. I do want to say something about the term
I used, and I have to maybe come up with a more
precise term. By double דרבנן, derabanan, I don't mean two דרבננים, derabananim,
right? I mean I mean if I could transgress two דרבננים derabananim
at one time, I could eat let's think. I could eat a
meat and milk. Right. I could do like I could no, I
could eat like a like a salami and cheese sandwich, which is
only דרבנן derabanan because they're not cooked together, and I don't know
the very fact that I'm putting them on top of one another,
you know, and eating them you know whatever is also דרבנן. derabanan.
So I've transgressed two דרבננים. derabananim. Okay, so that makes it worse,
not bad. Okay. Or I could do it while I'm reading לאור
הנר le-or ha-ner on שבת Shabbat and I'm then you know I'm
transgressing two דרבננים. derabananim. But what I said, a double דרבנן derabanan
and maybe there needs to be a better term, means that it's
that it's only a דרבנן derabanan on top, you know sort of
of a something
that
already is only a rabbinic problem. It's like גזירה לגזירה, gezeira le-gezeira,
but a גזירה לגזירה gezeira le-gezeira no no no, a גזירה לגזירה
gezeira le-gezeira is from the outset we make a double safeguard. This
is two separate things that intersect. Don't roll up something, even אוגדו
בידו, ogdo beyado, okay, and that's one type of a thing, from
any domain to any other domain, you know whatever. And then here
it happens to be that it's a case of a כרמלית, karmelit,
which is begins with as a rabbinic problem. So it's don't do
this thing, you know, which is you know, which even if it's
a problem, even if you have gone against this problem, you're only
doing it within rabbinic territory. So it's a type of גזירה לגזירה,
gezeira le-gezeira, but it's more by the way they intersected, not as
though it was intentionally you know made as a double safeguard.
I know a good one. Yes. The cheese on top of the
salami, and the cheese had not been produced strictly kosher except the
non-Jew didn't put in
the...
Okay right, גבינת עכו"ם. gevinat akum. Right, so good, גבינת עכו"ם gevinat
akum on top of the salami. That's where you're transgressing two דרבננים.
derabananim. But a דרבנן derabanan of a דרבנן derabanan would be I
don't know, let's say you know let's say we assume that electricity
when it's not incandescent lights is rabbinic. And let's say we assume
that that reading by a lamp that has an adjustable you know
knob on it is the same as the גזירה gezeira of reading
לאור הנר. le-or ha-ner. So if I were to be reading by
whatever there's discussions about all of these things. So if I were
to be reading by a lamp that is you know not incandescent,
it's
like fluorescent. Yeah, an LED? Right. These are the fluorescents, right? They
don't heat up a metal, do they? They actually do.
No, it's a gas inside.
No, the halogens, no, the halogens are the ones that could be
similar to incandescent. No, but fluorescent. So anyway, let's say I'm reading
by LEDs don't. Let's say I'm reading by an adjustable fluorescent light,
okay? So A, it's a rabbinic problem about reading לאור הנר, le-or
ha-ner, but the נר ner itself is only a rabbinic נר, ner,
right? So that would be you know it makes it weaker. It's
a דרבנן derabanan of a דרבנן, derabanan, not two דרבננים derabananim but
a דרבנן derabanan of a דרבנן. derabanan. Okay, anyway, that's how the
גמרא Gemara explains this issue of rolling it up from the כרמלית.
karmelit. Let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, וליחוש דילמא משתלי ומייתי להו ברשות הרבים ואייתי להו בהדיא לרשות
היחיד. ve-lichush dilma mishtali u-maytei lehu bi-reshut harabim ve-aytei lehu be-hedya le-reshut
hayachid. So the גמרא Gemara says no, who says? Maybe you'll pick
it up, it fell in the street, you'll finish reading what you
need to read in the street, and then you'll bring it back
into your house. Again that seems like just a very unlikely scenario,
but why don't we still worry about that? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says okay here's another explanation. הא מני בן עזאי היא דאמר מהלך
כעומד דמי *Ha mani Ben Azzai hi d'amar mahalech k'omed dami*. There's
a position of בן עזאי *Ben Azzai* going back way to the
beginning of מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat. *Masechet Shabbos*, okay, which says that
walking is like standing. You know every step you take you're pausing
for a second similar to that discussion about passing it across your
body. And therefore if you walk through a כרמלית *Carmelis*, the very
fact that you're walking and you're not throwing it through the כרמלית
*Carmelis* is like you stopped in the כרמלית *Carmelis*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ודילמא זרק ליה מזרק *V'deilma zarik leih mizrak*, maybe
you'll go pick it up in the רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshus
harabim*, finish reading, and then throw it into your house. I understand,
so דאמר רבי יוחנן מודה בן עזאי בזורק *d'amar Rabbi Yochanan modeh
Ben Azzai b'zorek*, בן עזאי *Ben Azzai* agrees if you throw it
that obviously it's not considered to stop. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אמר רב Rav אחא בר אבא זאת אומרת אין מזרקין כתבי
הקודש kitvei hakodesh. *amar Rav Acha bar Abba zos omeres ein mizrakin
kisvei hakodesh*. You don't throw holy books, you know that. All right
anyway, the basic reason is why is a סקופא *skofah* different? Because
it's a כרמלית *Carmelis*, not a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid *reshus hayachid*.
Now we get back to the case of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*
about the house that's a רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid. *reshus hayachid*, and
there there's three opinions. It has to be higher than ten טפחים
tefachim, *tefachim*, it has to be just a hair's breadth off of
the רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshus harabim*, okay, and even in the
רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *reshus harabim*, again since you're holding onto the
other end, it's only rabbinic and that's allowed to protect כתבי הקודש
kitvei hakodesh. *kisvei hakodesh*. היה קורא בראש הגג *Hayah korei b'rosh hagag*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first says ומי שרי *u'mi
sharei*? Is it really permissible to put if you can't roll it
up, to flip it over and have the script, you know, face
the wall? והתניא *V'hatanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *Braisa*, כותבי ספרים
תפילין ומזוזות *kosvei sefarim tefillin u'mezuzos*, people whose jobs are סופרים *soferim*,
they write, you know, ספרי תורה *sifrei Torah*, תפילין *tefillin*, מזוזות *mezuzos*.
And then I don't know you have to go and go to
the bathroom or go out to lunch. So what do you do?
You have all of your, you have your ספר תורה *sefer Torah*
open there that you're in the middle of doing it. How do
you do it to show it like respect and to protect it?
So לא התירו להן להפוך יריעה על פניה *lo hitiru lahen l'hafoch
yeriah al paneha*, they didn't say oh turn it upside down and
have the written part face the, you know, be face the table.
אלא *Ella*, what do you do? פורס עליה את הבגד *pors aleha
es habeged*, you put like some type of a cover on it.
That's more respectful. So how come here you're allowed to flip it
against the wall? So again the answer's quite obvious, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says התם אפשר הכא לא אפשר *hasam efshar hacha
lo efshar*. There
you can put a cover over it, here you can't put a
cover. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says why can't you put a cover
over it? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says well maybe you don't have
an available cover. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says why do you need
such a reason? You can't put a cover over it because you're
not allowed to take something and take it from the רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid *reshus hayachid* and put it into the airspace of or
whatever the airspace over רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *reshus harabim* even if
it's only suspended over the airspace. Now that actually is an interesting
question. Is that really a violation? I can go from רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid? *reshus hayachid* to מקום פטור makom patur. *makom patur*, and
if this thing is,
you know, if it's could I go ahead and could I intentionally
have done that if it weren't כתבי הקודש kitvei hakodesh. *kisvei hakodesh*?
Could I intentionally have thrown my coat over? I'm basically taking it
from רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, *reshus hayachid* to this מקום פטור makom
patur. *makom patur* over רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *reshus harabim*, it's like
a מקום פטור makom patur *makom patur*. What have I done wrong?
I've put it into a מקום פטור makom patur? *makom patur* and
it's not even fully in the מקום פטור makom patur, *makom patur*.
So maybe, maybe תוספות Tosafot's *Tosafos*'s problem is is that since we
said that this is only a problem of rolling it up when
it's within ten, so maybe I could put my בגד *beged* all
the way up until ten, but once I'm going to try to
put my cover down to cover the bottom of it, right, then
I'm getting it into the airspace of רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *reshus
harabim*. So presumably that's what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says is the reason
that I cannot put the cover. Okay so fine, you don't have
that as an option. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואי לא
אפיך איכא ביזיון כתבי הקודש טפי *v'ei lo apich ika bizayon kisvei
hakodesh tefei*, and if you don't flip it over then it'll be
even more of a disgrace to the כתבי הקודש *kisvei hakodesh*, and
therefore this is the best you can do in a bad circumstance.
Okay now הופכו על הכתב *hofcho al haksav*. Now we're going to
talk about this debate about עשרה טפחים asara tfachim. *asarah tefachim* or
a hair's breadth or on the ground. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
question is even if it's within עשרה טפחים asara tfachim, *asarah tefachim*
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, והא לא נח *v'ha lo nach*? It
didn't come to a resting place, it's suspended in mid-air, right? So
if it's within עשרה טפחים asara tfachim? *asarah tefachim* here, right, if
it were on a little platform and it was within עשרה טפחים
tefachim *asarah tefachim*, then it would be considered it rested in רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim, *reshus harabim*. So and now if you roll it
up it's דרבנן *d'rabonon* because you're holding one end. If you actually
if the whole thing had fallen and you had moved it, but
since half of it is there, it's only דרבנן *d'rabonon*. But that's
when it's actually resting in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim, *reshus harabim*. Here
it's suspended in mid-air. So even if it's in the airspace, the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s saying that shouldn't even be a rabbinic problem, it's
not really if it's not resting, it's not like it's there if
it's not on anything.
You didn't do an
עקירה *akirah*, you're not doing an עקירה *akirah*. So it's not even
a rabbinic problem. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so אמר ליה
אביי amar lei abaye *amar leih Abaye* I'm sorry so אמר רבא
Rava בכותל משופע bekotel meshupeh, *amar Rava b'kosel meshupa*. We're dealing with
a wall that's at an angle. Now again it's a pretty funny
wall and but a basic way to an easier way than saying
the wall at the angle means let's say there is something jutting
out of the wall. Okay, there's some type of a platform that's
you know some type of a of a of a thing that's
jutting out of the wall and when it falls it falls onto
it, does come to a rest, and it came to a rest
right within... ten טפחים. tefachim Okay, so yes, it's a scenario that
it did come to a rest, but you're right, if it were
totally suspended it would not be a problem at all. So אמר
ליה amar lei, אביי Abaye so אביי said back to him,
במאי אוקימתא למתניתין, bemai okimta lematnitin, what are you saying the mishnah
is talking about? בכותל משופע, bekotel meshupeh, that the wall is you
know slanted or whatever, it came to rest on a platform. So
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the end. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו
אינו מסולק מן הארץ אלא מלא חוט גוללו אצלו. Rabbi Yehuda omer
afilu eino mesulak min ha'aretz ela melo chut golelo etzlo. Even if
it's only a hair's breadth, you can roll it up. Now we
would say how is there a platform a hair's breadth off the
ground? Right? But the Gemara is saying even let's assume that there
is that scenario. The platform that it's resting on is a hair's
breadth off the ground. But if that's true, the Gemara says then
it's like it's resting, it's like it's on the ground of רשות
הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. It's within three טפחים, tefachim it's at a rest,
why is he how do you explain why he's allowing that? Now
remember this is only rabbinic because the guy at the top of
the roof is holding the other end. But presumably the first two
opinions do not allow a transgression of a rabbinic prohibition. So the
Gemara says והנח והנח? ve'hanach ve'hanach? It came to rest, it's right
on you know it's within three טפחים tefachim, of the ground of
רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. How could he allow you to roll it
up if it really is at rest? Presumably רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
case is that it's suspended in midair. Says the Gemara, חסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני. chasorei mechasra vehachi katani. Fine, you're right. Actually, there's more
like there's two opinions in the mishnah, not three. So there's two
cases. במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when says the you know
these are the words we're reading in, when is this that it
has that when it's within ten טפחים tefachim. it's a problem? בכותל
משופע, when it is a slanted wall, meaning when it's jutting out
and it came to rest. Then within ten טפחים tefachim? is a
problem. אבל, aval, top of צט עמוד ב, tzadik tet amud bet,
בכותל שאינו משופע, bekotel she'eino meshupeh, if it's not a slanted wall,
meaning if it's suspended in midair,
then למעלה משלושה גוללו אצלו למטה משלושה הופכו על הכתב. lemala mishlosha
golelo etzlo lemata mishlosha hofcho al haktav. Then we're totally reading a
brand new opinion in the mishnah. Then it's not ten higher or
lower than ten טפחים, tefachim it's higher or lower than three טפחים.
tefachim Because what's the significance of three טפחים? tefachim, Three right,
ten טפחים tefachim. is the air space of רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim.
but three טפחים tefachim is connected to the ground. So the Gemara
is saying like this, the opinion in the mishnah of ten טפחים,
tefachim you're right, that has to assume a scenario that it came
to some rest or else it wouldn't make sense why we're being
מחמיר. machmir. The other opinions about a hair's breadth or not and
we'll also that's about whether it's considered to actually be on the
ground. And there I will say that the opinion becomes one there
becomes a third opinion of three טפחים. tefachim So the Gemara is
now constructing it that when it did not come at rest, we
have three possibilities: that within three טפחים tefachim is a problem because
let me do this anyway, within three טפחים tefachim is a problem
because that is defined as לבוד, lavud, so that's already a problem
and it's no good. It's rabbinic again, but it's a problem. The
other says no, as long as it's you know a hair's breadth
off the ground you're okay, that it's not going to even when
it's in לבוד, lavud, it's only a problem once it hits the
ground. Only hitting the ground really counts. And then רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that says I don't care even if it hit the ground
it's rabbinic and you're protecting כתבי הקודש. So basically the debate of
the first two opinions is if something is within three טפחים tefachim,
of the ground of רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim is it considered like
it's actually resting on the ground? Okay, and would picking it up
from midair be a problem? So the Gemara now looks at the
way it reconstructed the argument, what is the issue what's the difference
between three טפחים tefachim. and a hair's breadth? You know both of
those when once you're within three טפחים tefachim, it shouldn't make a
difference. So let's take a look at how the Gemara now explains
the positions based on its reconstruction. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו אינו מסולק
מן הארץ, Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu eino mesulak min ha'aretz, even if
it's only a hair's breadth. So the Gemara says why? דיבעינן הנחה
על גבי משהו, deba'inan hanacha al gabi mashehu, that even if it's
within three טפחים, tefachim you need it to come to rest on
physically on something. You know even it's not enough, anything that is
suspended it's not enough, even if it's within three טפחים. tefachim So
and therefore he says you're okay here. ואי הא דאמר רבא, ve'ei
ha de'amar Rava, but one minute, Rava said, קלוטה בתוך שלושה לרבנן
צריך הנחה, keluta betoch shelosha lerabbanan tzarich hanacha, that the rabbis, meaning
in a different debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of קלוטה כמי
שהונחה, keluta k'mi she'hunacha, if you remember that, again we're hearkening back
to the beginning of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbat. Anyway, even the rabbis,
even the more lenient opinion says that if it's in the air
space within three טפחים, tefachim I'm sorry, even the rabbis that are
more strict, anyway they said once it's that within three טפחים tefachim
it needs צריך הנחה. tzarich hanacha. It needs three טפחים tefachim is
not enough, it needs to actually physically be placed down on the
ground. לימא כתנאי אמרה לשמעתתא? leima ketannai amrah lishmatata? So maybe he's
saying maybe this is really a debate of תנאים? tannaim? Because what
has the Gemara now said? The Gemara said like this, there are
two scenarios. One scenario is it comes to land on a platform.
Okay, there once it's within ten טפחים tefachim you've got a problem.
That's the ten טפחים tefachim of the mishnah. But the other scenario
is what we thought all along, that it is suspended in midair.
And then the Gemara is saying that there's a three-way debate. Okay,
there's one debate that says within three טפחים tefachim is a problem
because let me do this anyway, within three טפחים tefachim is a
problem because that is defined as לבוד, lavud, so that's already a
problem and it's no good. It's rabbinic again, but it's a problem.
The other says no, as long as it's you know a hair's
breadth off the ground you're okay, that it's not going to even
when it's in לבוד, lavud, it's only a problem once it hits
the ground. Only hitting the ground really counts. And then רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that says I don't care even if it hit the
ground it's rabbinic and you're protecting כתבי הקודש. So basically the debate
of the first two opinions is if something is within three טפחים
tefachim, of the ground of רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim. is it considered
like it's actually resting on the ground? Okay, and would picking it
up from midair be a problem? So the Gemara now looks at
the way it reconstructed the argument, what is the issue what's the
difference between three טפחים tefachim. and a hair's breadth? You know both
of those when once you're within three טפחים tefachim, it shouldn't make
a difference. So let's take a look at how the Gemara now
explains the positions based on its reconstruction. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו אינו
מסולק מן הארץ, Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu eino mesulak min ha'aretz, even
if it's only a hair's breadth. So the Gemara says why? דיבעינן
הנחה על גבי משהו, deba'inan hanacha al gabi mashehu, that even if
it's within three טפחים, tefachim you need it to come to rest
on physically on something. You know even it's not enough, anything that
is suspended it's not enough, even if it's within three טפחים. tefachim
So and therefore he says you're okay here. ואי הא דאמר רבא,
ve'ei ha de'amar Rava, but one minute, Rava said, קלוטה בתוך שלושה
לרבנן צריך הנחה, keluta betoch shelosha lerabbanan tzarich hanacha, that the rabbis,
meaning in a different debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of קלוטה
כמי שהונחה, keluta k'mi she'hunacha, if you remember that, again we're hearkening
back to the beginning of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbat. Anyway, even the
rabbis, even the more lenient opinion says that if it's in the
air space within three טפחים, tefachim I'm sorry, even the rabbis that
are more strict, anyway they said once it's
that within three טפחים tefachim it needs צריך הנחה. tzarich hanacha. It
needs three טפחים tefachim is not enough, it needs to actually physically
be placed down on the ground. לימא כתנאי אמרה לשמעתתא? leima ketannai
amrah lishmatata? So maybe he's saying maybe this is really a debate
of תנאים? tannaim? Because what has the Gemara now said? The Gemara
said like this, there are two scenarios.
One scenario is it comes to land on a platform.
Okay, there once it's within ten טפחים tefachim you've got a problem.
That's the ten טפחים tefachim of the mishnah. But the other scenario
is what we thought all along, that it is suspended in midair.
And then the Gemara is saying that there's a three-way debate. Okay,
there's one debate that says within three טפחים tefachim, is a problem
because let me do this anyway,
within three טפחים tefachim is a problem because that is defined as
לבוד, lavud, so that's already a problem and it's no good. It's
rabbinic again, but it's a problem. The other says no, as long
as it's you know a hair's breadth off the ground you're okay,
that it's not going to even when it's in לבוד, lavud, it's
only a problem once it hits the ground. Only hitting the ground
really counts. And then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says I don't
care even if it hit the ground it's rabbinic and you're protecting
כתבי הקודש. So basically the debate of the first two opinions is
if something is within three טפחים tefachim of the ground of רשות
הרבים, Reshut HaRabim is it considered like it's actually resting on the
ground? Okay, and would picking it up from midair be a problem?
So the Gemara. The Gemara גמרא Gemara, says, well, Rava רבא Rava
has an opinion about that. Rava רבא Rava says that even within
three tefachim טפחים, tefachim it's not a problem unless it's actually resting
on the ground. So why isn't Rava רבא Rava this debate of
Tannaim תנאים Tannaim actually a debate of Rava's רבא Rava position? And
an Amora אמורא Amora usually would like to think that everybody goes
like his position. Okay, so the Gemara's גמרא Gemara saying you have
now framed it that the debate of the first two opinions is
whether within three tefachim טפחים tefachim needs to be put on the
ground. So would we say that they're debating Rava's רבא position?
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara, says, Ella kulei Rebbe Yehuda hi אלא
כולי רבי יהודה היא. Ella kulei Rebbe Yehuda hi. Fine. Take out
the three tefachim טפחים tefachim. position. It's all Reb Yehuda. Vechisorei mechasra
vehachi kateni חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Vechisorei mechasra vehachi kateni, and here's
how it's read. Bemai devarim amurim במה דברים אמורים, Bemai devarim amurim,
another, well, once we're changing we're changing. Bemai devarim amurim במה דברים
אמורים, Bemai devarim amurim, bekotel hamishupah בכותל המשופע. bekotel hamishupah. When is
ten tefachim טפחים tefachim relevant, less than ten tefachim טפחים tefachim a
problem, when it hits, when it lands on a platform. Okay, bekotel
hamishupah בכותל המשופע. bekotel hamishupah. Aval bekotel she’eino mishupah אבל בכותל שאינו
משופע, aval bekotel she’eino mishupah, if it's suspended in midair, afilu pacho
mishlosha tefachim אפילו פחות משלושה טפחים, afilu pacho mishlosha tefachim, golo etzlo
גוללו אצלו. golo etzlo. Then it could be even within three tefachim
טפחים. tefachim, SheRebbe Yehuda omer שרבי יהודה אומר, SheRebbe Yehuda omer, afilu
eino mesulak min ha'aretz ella mela nima golo etzlo אפילו אינו מסולק
מן הארץ אלא מלא נימא גוללו אצלו. afilu eino mesulak min ha'aretz
ella mela nima golo etzlo. Because Reb Yehuda says as long as
it's a hairsbreadth off, mai ta'ama מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Be'inan hanacha
gabei mashehu בעינן הנחה גבי משהו, be’inan hanacha gabei mashehu, because it's
not a problem unless it's actually physically on something. Okay, so what
the Gemara גמרא Gemara is saying now is that there are not
three opinions as I said before, but really two opinions. If it
comes to rest on a platform, then it's actually then it's resting
in Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim. and then ten tefachim טפחים
tefachim is Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, the airspace of Reshut
HaRabim רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. If it's suspended, then that's the ten
tefachim טפחים tfachim, scenario when it's actually resting on something. Then if
it's suspended you have two opinions. You have Reb Yehuda's position that
says as long as it's within a hairsbreadth of the ground you're
okay, because even if it's within three tefachim טפחים, tfachim it is
not a Shabbos problem unless it's actually physically at rest. So that's
Reb Yehuda's idea, even within a hairsbreadth you're okay, it has to
physically be at rest, three tefachim טפחים tfachim, is not a problem.
And Reb Shimon says even if it's on the ground I don't
have a problem because yes, it's a rabbinic prohibition but I will
allow that for the sake of protecting Kevod HaBriyot כבוד הבריות. Kevod
HaBriyot. Okay, so those are the opinions in the Mishnah. Now we
go on to the next case, a new Mishnah. Ziz she'lifnei chalon
זיז שלפני חלון, Ziz she'lifnei chalon, noten alav venoten mimenu beShabbat נותנין
עליו ונותנין ממנו בשבת. noten alav venoten mimenu beShabbat. Okay, you have
a nice little hypothetical case, although
it's again going to be with something facing the Reshut HaRabim רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, if you have
here's your nice little window and outside of your window you've got
a nice little thing where you have your, I don't know, you
have your flower pots, right? It looks like a flower.
Your sun tea.
You got your little cup or something. Okay, fine, let's, and there's
your window. Okay, anyway, and you use that little platform outside and
down here is a Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Do I
have to be concerned that if I'm using my little, what they
call, not a what's that little thing that sticks out from a
window called, ledge? Right, if I'm using my ledge it might fall
down into Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים reshut harabim. and go from a
Reshut HaYachid רשות היחיד reshut hayachid? to a Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. Do I have to be concerned? And the Mishnah says
you do not.
Ziz she'lifnei chalon זיז שלפני חלון, Ziz she'lifnei chalon, you have a
little ledge, noten alav venoten mimenu beShabbat נותנין עליו ונותנין ממנו בשבת,
noten alav venoten mimenu beShabbat, you can put things, you know, take
your little cup and, you know, whatever, put things in and out
from that on Shabbat. Okay, to your house. Okay, so the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says, hai ziz demafik leheicha האי זיז דמפיק להיכא? hai
ziz demafik leheicha? Where is this little ledge sort of jutting out
into? What's, you know, what is it over? Ileima demafik leReshut HaRabim
אילימא דמפיק לרשות הרבים, ileima demafik leReshut HaRabim, if it's jutting out
into the Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים reshut harabim, like the thing that
I drew, leichush shema nafal ve'ati le'asuyei ליחוש שמא נפל ואתי לאתויי.
leichush shema nafal ve'ati le'asuyei. Let's be afraid that your thing will
fall to the ground. Now that itself is not a problem because
you know, it would be a, not only wouldn't be a, would
be a shogeg שוגג, shogeg, it would be like an onnes אונס,
onnes, right? I mean if it accidentally fell, that's like mitaseik מתעסק,
mitaseik, onnes אונס, onnes, we're not concerned about that. But what we're
concerned about is once it falls to the ground, you're going to
run out and pick it up and bring it back in. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ella demafik leReshut HaYachid אלא דמפיק לרשות
היחיד. ella demafik leReshut HaYachid. Okay, so it's, you know, it's over
your backyard which is as we know, chatzer חצר chatzer is Reshut
HaYachid רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So if that's true, peshita פשיטא? peshita?
Then there's no chiddush חידוש chiddush at all. So either it's completely
obvious or it doesn't make sense. So amar Abaye אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, le'olam demafik leReshut HaRabim לעולם דמפיק לרשות הרבים. le'olam demafik leReshut
HaRabim. No, it's jutting out into the Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim, Umai noten alav de'katani ומאי נותנין עליו דקתני? umai noten alav
de'katani? Keilim hanishbarim כלים הנשברים. keilim hanishbarim. What can you put on
it? You can put on it fragile vessels. So therefore, things that
would break. So if it were to fall down and break, you
wouldn't pick it up. Okay, so you can put your teacup on
it but you can't put your, I don't know what, your pillow
on it.
You can't clean it up though.
All right, well, that conscientious we're not, we're not afraid of. Okay,
so tanya nami hachi תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught
similarly. Ziz she'lifnei chalon
זיז שלפני חלון, Ziz she'lifnei chalon, if you have a ledge coming
out of a window, hayotzei leReshut HaRabim היוצא לרשות הרבים, hayotzei leReshut
HaRabim, that's jutting out over Reshut HaRabim רשות הרבים, reshut harabim noten
alav katarot vekhossot נותנין עליו קתראות וכוסות, noten alav katarot vekhossot, plates
and and cups, kitoniyot קיטוניות, kitoniyot, pitchers, vetzelochiyot וצלוחיות, vetzelochiyot, and also
types of
plates, bowls, what, platters? Thank you. Umishtamesh bekohl ha... So anyway, so
Rashi רש"י Rashi says the tanya nami hachi תניא נמי הכי tanya
nami hachi is that all these are implicitly breakable objects.
Okay, umishtamesh bekohl hakotel ומשתמש בכל הכותל. umishtamesh bekohl hakotel. Now we
introduce a new point.
Right, it's, you're right. I know, it's quite crazy. It's like you
never find, and it's not even like a formal category, you know,
it's completely, you know, and it's like and Dov is absolutely correct.
Now normally whatever motivates חז"ל, Chazal, then they make a, you know,
like an absolute rule. You can or you can't. Right here it's
basically saying, oh, when the גזירה gezeira is relevant, then you can,
when it's not, you know, then you can. I know you like
that. I know because you don't like all those categorical things, but
it is very יוצא מן הכלל. yotzei min haklal. Anyway, now it
says like this, ומשתמש
בכל אותן עד עשרה תחתונים.
u'mishtamesh be'chol
otan ad asara tachtonim. Also, the way I'll read it the way
תוספות Tosafot reads it, if you happen to have, you know, I
don't know, various like holes or, you know, in the wall, and
you can like, you know, here you are whatever and you want
to reach over, you know, they would use it, they would use
little holes in the wall and put stuff into a hole in
the wall, other ways of using the wall, in addition to the
ledge, that's okay as long as it's all taking place above the
עשרה טפחים. tefachim Okay, once you are using anything within the עשרה
טפחים, then you're going from your רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and, you
know, into the airspace of the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim Okay, so
anything you're doing on that wall is fine, just keep it above
the waist. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so where were we?
Okay, ואם יש זיז אחד למטה הימנו משתמש בו ובעליון אין משתמש
בו אלא כנגד חלונו ve'im yesh ziz echad lemata heimenu mishtamesh bo
u've'elyon ein mishtamesh bo ela kineged chalono
and if you have actually two ledges, not, I mean, it's sort
of a long תוספות's way, not, you know, not, you know, not
holes, but you've got like another ledge here, so another ledge you
can use even if it's not exactly underneath, by your window. But
your own ledge, you can only use in the space that's directly
in front of your window. So in theory, you know, if this
ledge went, I don't know, like all the way around like that,
right, you had, you know, some, you know, sometimes they have ledges,
right, like that, all, you know, they're connected or whatever, you can
only use the part of the ledge in front of your window.
But some ledge that's lower, that you could use even not in
front. So what logic is that? Right? So that's what the גמרא
Gemara, says, that doesn't make any sense. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara So it says, ובעליון אין משתמש בו אלא
כנגד חלונו, u've'elyon ein mishtamesh bo ela kineged chalono,
only opposite your window. So the גמרא Gemara, says, האי זיז היכי
דמי? hai ziz heichi dami? What's, what's the story with this זיז?
ziz? אי דלית ביה ארבע, ei d'leit bei arba, if there isn't
four, then מקום פטור הוא. makom patur hu. It's a מקום פטור.
makom patur. Now, it's really not then, ואפילו כנגד חלונו נמי לא
ישתמש, v'afillu kineged chalono nami lo ishtamesh,
you shouldn't even use it by your window. Now that is a
crazy line in the גמרא, because number one, we've been assuming that
the ledge is not its, first of all, I haven't spelled this
out, I was waiting for someone to ask. Okay, but why do
we assume, and we've assumed it in a lot of cases, that
this ledge is a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid Even if the ledge
is ten by four, right, it doesn't have any walls, right? So
the basic assumption is that what, I'm
assuming it's above, what is it? עשרה טפחים?
Yeah, it might be ten טפחים, but remember we need it to
be a platform ten טפחים so the walls go up, right? If
you have something that if you have, we had this case before,
right? If you were to have a case that were that was
like this,
like a wide
ledge, if you were to have something like that, right, we say
that it's not a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid even though this is
ten by four high, it doesn't have walls. So why is this
a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid, So תוספות basically says, it doesn't matter,
if there are no walls,
it's connected to the wall of your house.
So תוספות says it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, by virtue of
it being, as Michael says, connected to your house, and there's a
principle in the גמרא called חורי. chori. Okay, like
חורי רשות היחיד chorei reshut hayachid or חורי רשות הרבים. chorei reshut
harabim. Okay, which is, and then it becomes like just a part
of the existing רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, or רשות הרבים. reshut harabim,
So this anyway. So therefore there's two things which is crazy about
this גמרא, three things, מקום פטור. makom patur. Number one is מקום
פטור makom patur, is a permissible space. Number two is that why
is it a מקום פטור? makom patur If, you know, the whole
thing is part of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because it's connected to
your house, yes or no, should it make a difference? And number
three is, well, I guess it's what I said is number one,
so you know, big deal, why all of a sudden does that
create a problem? Even if it is a מקום פטור, why does
it create a problem? So basically רש"י Rashi says it doesn't really
mean it. The הגר"א HaGra takes the words out. Okay, so the
basic so the basic point is let's read it without the phrase
of מקום פטור. It says like this, האי זיז היכי דמי? hai
ziz heichi dami? What's the case about this זיז? ziz? אי דלית
ביה ארבע, ei d'leit bei arba, if it's not four טפחים, then
הוא אפילו כנגד חלונו נמי לא ישתמש. hu afillu kineged chalono nami
lo ishtamesh.
So
forget מקום פטור. רש"י effectively takes it out. So I don't understand,
you shouldn't even use it by your window. Now why not? Why
does if you're forgetting מקום פטור, מקום פטור wasn't relevant, why shouldn't
you use it if it's less than four? So רש"י says because
if it's so narrow, then things are definitely going to fall off.
Okay. So therefore if it's so
if less than four matters, then it should be a prob because
it's too... too narrow, then it should be a problem even if
it's directly in front of your window. ואי איכא ארבעה V'ee ikka
arba'ah and if it is four wide בכולי כותל נשתמש bechulei kotel
nistamesh then you should be able to use it anywhere on the
wall. Why is it that there's this limit about directly in front
of your window or somewhere else and why does it matter if
it's the upper ledge or the lower ledge? So the גמרא'ס Gemara's
answer is pretty arbitrary and doesn't really make it about the upper
or the lower ledge per se. Let's take a look. אמר אביי
Amar Abaye תחתון דאית ביה ארבעה. tachton d'it bei arba'ah. When we
say you can use other ledges even not opposite to your window,
that's when it's got ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim and therefore it's a
reasonable space and we're not afraid that things are going to fall.
עליון Elyon but this scenario is that the one directly by your
window is לית ביה ארבעה leit bei arba'ah doesn't have ארבעה טפחים
arba'ah tefachim וחלון משלימו לעשרה vechalon mashlimo l'asarah
and the window because you know if you have a ledge outside
of your window then there's also the space inside of your, you
know, of your window that combines to it to make it sufficient
space. Okay. כנגד חלון משתמש Keneged chalon mishtamesh
and opposite your window you can use it and here's the phrase
דחורי חלון הוא dechorei chalon hu it's a hole of the window
meaning it's like, you know, it's part of your, it's an extension
of the ledge. דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא אסור dehai gisa u'dehai gisa
asur on one side or the other side of your window it's
forbidden. So what the גמרא basically has said is, you know, it's
completely arbitrary that it talks about using a lower ledge. The way
the גמרא is explaining this is, is that this is a very
narrow ledge. Okay? And if this is a very narrow ledge, right,
it's only it's only, you know, it's only two טפחים here, so
anywhere over here you can't use it because it'll definitely fall. If
you're using it directly opposite your window, then you use, then you'll
wind up, you know, balancing it, you know, it'll get stability by
going inside of your window and in this
case it was a bottom ledge.
What? Yeah. So then in the end it doesn't matter bottom or
top or whatever, it just means a narrow ledge you have to
use only, can use only in front of your window. All right.
Next משנה. Mishnah. See, we're just plowing along. Next משנה. Mishnah עומד
אדם ברשות היחיד. Omed adam b'reshut hayachid. Now we get to cases,
not just of גזירות gezeirot or whatever special cases, but we get
to really defining הוצאה. hotza'ah. So it's so funny again how much
this פרק perek is, you know, is related to more of מסכת
masechet שבת. Shabbat. So עומד אדם ברשות היחיד ומטלטל ברשות הרבים. Omed
adam b'reshut hayachid u'metaltel b'reshut harabim. The person can stand in רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid. and carry and move things in a רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. So here I am, I
need a picture for this, but whatever. Right? You're just
in an
artistic mood.
I'm in an artistic mood.
Here's your house. Okay? And here's your רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. You
can stand somehow, I don't know, in the doorframe of your house,
okay, you're in your רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, and you are reaching
over and you're moving an object, you know, from one place to
another in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Now you're not moving it ארבע
אמות arba amot in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim but we're not afraid
that if you are reaching out and moving an object in a
רשות הרבים, you're going to come and bring the object back into
רשות היחיד, which seems like a very reasonable thing to be afraid
of. And in reverse, you can stand out in the רשות הרבים
and move, stick your hands into somebody's house and move objects around
and we're not afraid you'll come to bring it in to you.
Okay. So עומד אדם ברשות... Omed adam b'reshut... you said you're not
afraid
because if you were in רשות הרבים you could move something less
than ארבע אמות.
arba amot. Right,
although here the natural thing is like just to pull it back,
you know.
It's a חידוש chiddush that's, right.
Right, I mean, yeah, that's why it's a חידוש chiddush because normally,
no, no, well, actually, it's... no, right, it's actually similar that we're
not afraid but here there's much more reason to think you'd be
afraid. Right. עומד אדם ברשות היחיד ומטלטל ברשות הרבים, Omed adam b'reshut
hayachid u'metaltel b'reshut harabim, ברשות הרבים ומטלטל ברשות היחיד, b'reshut harabim u'metaltel
b'reshut hayachid, ובלבד שלא יוציא חוץ מארבע אמות. u'bilvad shelo yotzi chutz
m'arba amot.
Obviously, if we're letting you stand in your house and move in
רשות הרבים, don't move it ארבע אמות arba amot in רשות הרבים.
You're no better than a guy who's actually in the street. Okay,
but we're not afraid that if you move it less than ארבע
אמות, arba amot, we're not afraid you'll come to or in the
reverse you'll come to pull it back to where you are. So
the גמרא will discuss, I know. We normally use the entire מסכת
of all these דרבננס derabbanans that, you know, half of them we
don't understand like how much are you concerned about and here it's
like a completely reasonable that it would come to lead to a
דאורייתא. d'Oraita.
The other way I would say that if you're in, if you're
in רשות היחיד, maybe you can move something more than ארבע אמות
arba amot in רשות הרבים.
Why? You picked something up and you carried it and you placed
it down. Why does it matter where your body is?
I guess the question is, are you carrying or is it the
object is based off of the person with the hand.
Yeah, but it always focuses on the object. Okay. So now the
גמרא says that's case number one. Now the משנה Mishna says לא
יעמוד אדם ברשות היחיד וישתין ברשות הרבים. Lo ya'amod adam b'reshut hayachid
v'yashtin b'reshut harabim. Don't stand in רשות היחיד and urinate into the
רשות הרבים. Talking, what? Very, right, very, I was about to say
that, very male-centric again. ברשות הרבים וישתין ברשות היחיד B'reshut harabim v'yashtin
b'reshut hayachid or the reverse, because there, I mean, if you're basically
the object, urine, is starting in one location and being moved to
the other.
Okay.
וכן לא ירוק, V'chein lo yarok, you should not spit. because the
spit starts in one location and is going to the other location.
That, these, look, in places where they did not have indoor plumbing
and they urinated on the streets and certainly they spat on the
streets, these are you have to talk about this stuff.
Didn't we all like, what, isn't water all connected though?
Alright, anyway, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer,
okay, אף משנתלש רוקו בפיו, af mishenitlash ruko befiv, from the moment
that the spittle is literally like
uprooted in your mouth, meaning you know, normally there's obviously liquid going
on in your mouth, otherwise your mouth would feel very dry, but
when you're ready to spit, it feels like it's more like a
separate object, like somehow it's not co- I don't know, there's obviously
some physical explanation, but I think people understand that experience about that
the spit is now separated in your mouth. Okay, and once that's
true, he says you're carrying spit in your mouth. And לא יהלך
ארבע אמות עד שירוק, lo yehalech arba amot ad sheyirok, you gotta
spit right away. Don't spit into a רשות היחיד. Okay, you have
to spit within ארבע אמות. arba amot. But this is a very
fascinating question, which is when is the spit in your mouth considered
distinct from you? Like it's a question on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
swallowing your own spit, right? So as long as it's obviously all
part of your mouth, it's okay, but if it says if somehow
the spit separates off, you know, and it's in your mouth, but
it's, you know, but it's sort of like a separate thing, then
it's like a liquid and you can't swallow it. So here too,
it's like you're carrying a liquid and you have to spit. Just
don't do it outside.
So it's okay if you're in the רשות הרבים you could spit?
No, no, he's building on. Obviously you can't spit from one domain
to the other. But not only that, even when it's up, even
when once it's separated in your mouth, you can't even walk ארבע
אמות. arba amot. So your only option is I can't spit into
רשות היחיד, I can't walk ארבע אמות, arba amot, I can't spit
it outside, the only thing you can do is spit right down
in front of you. Okay?
Okay.
The same thing like you could urinate in the same?
Yes, you could also urinate right down in front of you, I
think. Okay, מתני לה לרבי חיננא בר שלמיא, masni lah leRabbi Chinana
bar Shelmaya, גמרא, let's just get started. So מתני לה לרבי חיננא
בר שלמיא לחייא בר רב קמיה דרב. masni lah leRabbi Chinana bar
Shelmaya leChiya bar Rav kamei deRav. So רבי חיננא בר
שלמיא Rabbi Chinana bar Shelmaya taught this משנה Mishna to חייא, Chiya,
רב's Rav. son, directly in the presence of רב. Rav And here's
the version he had: לא יעמוד אדם ברשות היחיד וישתים ברשות הרבים.
lo ya'amod adam bereshut hayachid veyashtin bereshut harabim. So his version was
a person should not, as opposed to our משנה Mishna which says
you're allowed to stand in one domain, his version of the משנה
Mishna said you're not allowed to stand in one domain and move
into the other. So אמר ליה, so רב Rav said back to
him: שבקת רבנן ועבדת כרבי מאיר? shavkta rabanan ve'avdata keRabbi Meir? You're
abandoning the רבנן Rabanan and going like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Because
we're going to find a later משנה Mishna that רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir position says you're not allowed to do this. So his version
of the earlier משנה Mishna followed רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position and
also said you're not allowed. So רב says, what are you doing,
abandoning the רבנן Rabanan and taking like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
reading our earlier משנה Mishna like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So let's
just see the answer. The גמרא says: הוא סבר. hu savar. Now
רבי חיננא Rabbi Chinana assumed: מדסיפא רבי מאיר רישא נמי רבי מאיר.
mideseifa Rabbi Meir reisha nami Rabbi Meir. Since we're about to see
in another משנה Mishna, coming up, which is the end of this
משנה, Mishna that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position that you're not allowed
to do
it, he thought that was just repeating what the first משנה Mishna
had said. And therefore his version or the version that he embraced,
let's say, I don't know if he changed it, you know, there
could have been other versions going around, but anyway his version was:
You're not allowed to do it. ולא היא. velo hi. It's not
true. סיפא רבי מאיר ורישא רבנן. seifa Rabbi Meir vereisha rabanan. There's
really a debate. Our סתם משנה stam Mishna is the רבנן Rabanan
that says you're allowed to, and later there'll be a position of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says you're not allowed to. Okay, so
the גמרא, what? No, it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, so we
will that is where we are, that the משנה is you're allowed
to. Why you're allowed to, we will continue to discuss tomorrow on
שבת.
Okay. Things missing for מעריב. Maariv. Join for מעריב. Maariv. Do you
like orchestral music?
Somewhat.
I went to see one of the best concerts I've ever been
to. Really? Last night. They're doing another of the same program on
Tuesday. Who?
Where is it?
Philharmonic at...